An average man, Kaiji,
日々 怠惰で自堕落な生活を
送っていた平凡な男 カイジ
who lives a life of sloth and self-indulgence.
One day, suddenly, he is thrust deep into debt,
そのカイジに ある日突然
借金が降りかかる
due to having cosigned a friend's loan.
仲間の保証人になったことが
原因だった
To win forgiveness of that debt, he boards the Ship of Hope, Espoir.
借金をチャラにするため
乗り込んだのは
希望の船 ｢エスポワール｣
Kaiji is invited to an evening with the Devil.
カイジは悪魔の夜へと誘われる
罠 裏切り だまし合い
Traps! Betrayals! Cheats!
繰り広げられる狂気のギャンブル
The ultimate gamble unfolds!
そして幾多の困難を乗り越え
カイジは たどり着く
And Kaiji survives through it, to face...
The demon of the underworld and Teiai's CEO, Kazutaka Hyodo!
闇の世界に君臨する魔王
帝愛グループの総帥 兵藤和尊
だが しかし
But! But!!!
カイジは負けるべくして負け
兵藤は勝つべくして勝った
Kaiji, fated to lose, loses. Hyodo, fated to win, wins.
カイジは王の王たる所以を
手痛い代償を払い 思い知らされる
Kaiji, defeated by the King, is held to his debt.
Thus, the devil's night was sealed with Kaiji's blood!
こうして悪魔の夜に
ようやく終止符が打たれた
カイジの血によって
And as the seasons change!
そして季節が流れ…
チッ なんで出ねえんだよ！
Where the hell is he!?
何してくれてんだ オラ！
やべっ！
What's wrong with you!?
Oh shit.
あれから数ヵ月　カイジは
Several months have passed.
Kaiji is once again living a life of sloth and self-indulgence.
相変わらず
怠惰で自堕落な生活を送っていた
Where'd he go!?
だが 兵藤に敗れた時点での
カイジの借金は
But when Kaiji lost to Hyodo, his debt was already...
668万
6.8 million yen!
Further, treatment of his ear and fingers at an underground clinic cost another two million!
さらに闇医者による
指と耳の縫合手術の入院で200万
With interest factored in, his debts have reached 9.5 million yen!
その後 それに金利が加わり
借金は膨らみ950万
ついに数日前から帝愛グループに
追われる身となった
The Teiai Group has been in pursuit of him for several days.
But Kaiji does not yet know this!
だがカイジは
そのことをまだ知らない
Damn that walking trash!
クソッ クズが
Endoh, who had entered Kaiji in both
カイジに限定ジャンケンと
人間競馬を斡旋した 遠藤は
Restricted Rock, Paper, Scissors and the Human Derby,
利根川の失脚後
メーンの仕事を外され
after his failure lost his usual position
and was assigned to finding and "recovering" defaulted debtors.
失踪した劣悪債務者の捜査と
取り立ての仕事をしていた
カイジ
あ？
Kaiji!
あっ！遠藤さん
Hey, Endoh!
ラッキー！
迎えに来てくれたんすね？
Great! You came!
何？
俺 金に困ってましてね
Huh?
I'm kinda broke right now.
I wouldn't even be able to make the hundred thousand
これじゃあ借金1000万なんて
逆立ちしたって返せねえんすよ
if you turned me upside down and shook me out!
俺 何でもやりますから
紹介してくださいよ
I'll do anything! Just show me where the action is!
ギャンブル
クズが！
えっ？
You trash...
So, how are your ear and your fingers feeling?
お前 耳と指いかれてんだよな？
でも今度は絶対 勝ちますよ
This time I'll win! I swear it!
俺 自信があんだ　ほんとっすよ
I know I will!
Really!
あれだけの痛手を負って
まだ懲りずにギャンブルだ？
He's still trying to gamble after he went through that?
I thought he was better than this.
ちったあ
まともな奴かと思ったら…
It's sad. He's a total junkie.
哀れな 悲しいほどの
ジャンキーぶりだ
完全にいかれてる
Completely nuts.
ついてこい
さすが遠藤さん
Come with me.
I knew you'd come through, Endoh!
This time I'm really gonna win!
遠藤さん 俺 今度こそ
絶対勝ってみせますよ
Kaiji. There is no winning or losing.
カイジ君 ありゃしねえんだよ
勝つも負けるも
えっ？
You trash!
クズが！
睡眠剤だ
しばらく眠ってもらおう
That should knock you out for a while.
What are you going to do to me, you bastard!?
貴様… どうす… る気だ
You're going to work, you loan cheat.
働くんだよ　劣悪債務者はな
え？働くって…
Work...?
フフフ… まあまあ
それは起きた時のお楽しみ
You'll find out all about that when you wake up.
それは… 一体 どんな…
What kind of—
そうだな　地獄さ
Oh, right.
In Hell. Deep underground, just like it's supposed to be.
文字通りの地の獄
Kaiji, you owe about ten million, so it'll take you fifteen years or so to pay it off.
カイジ君の借金は
ほぼ1000万だから
まっ 15年は入ってもらう計算か
じ… 15？
Fif...teen?
そう　15年
Yeah, fifteen years.
降ろせ　降ろへ… 降ろへー…
Let... me out... Let me...
降ろひまへん
Never.
Hell
気がつけばカイジは地の獄
Kaiji awakens in the Abyss.
An unknown location, deep in the bowels of the earth!
どこか分からぬ地中の底の底
異様な熱気と騒音
粉塵 悪臭 不衛生
Hot and loud... Dusty, smelly, and unsafe...
A forced labor camp of the disappeared!
亡者巣くう強制労働の施設にいた
この工事は帝愛の幹部たちの
This is not only Teiai's nuclear shelter, but an entire underground kingdom!
核シェルターを兼ねた
超豪勢な地下王国造り
この劣悪な環境下で
働かされている者は
Just like Kaiji, forced to labor after his default,
皆 カイジと同じ
多額な負債を背負い確保された者
the other workers also bear deep debts.
Dammit!
クソッ
(笛の音)
作業終了！各班ごとに整列
Shift over!
Line up by group!
さっさと並べ！Ａ班 Ｂ班 行進
Hurry it up!
A group and B group, advance!
作業が終わると脱衣
そして シャワー
When their work is finished, they strip and shower!
That fucker tricked me!
クソッ ふざけやがって
Shit! Shit!
クソッ クソッ
クソッ！
おい 早くしてくれよ
Shit!
Then they eat!
そして食事
おかずは メザシとたくわんだけ
Their repast is nothing but dried sardines and pickled radish!
貧しい食事
A mere pittance!
When this is finished, they return to their rooms.
これが終わると部屋に戻る
This is E group's barracks, home to 23 men!
そこはＥ班23人の相部屋
Inside are old newspapers, old magazines, shogi and go boards, and cards.
あるのは古雑誌と古新聞
将棋 囲碁 トランプの類い
Night and day spent with one's comrades!
四六時中 仲間と一緒
朝も昼も夜も
This sucks...
ふざけろ
Woken at 5AM by an alarm,
朝５時 サイレンの音に
叩き起こされ
部屋の掃除 朝食の後 作業開始
they clean their room, eat breakfast, and return to work!
Apart from a short break for lunch, they work until evening!
昼食を挟み 夕方まで働かされる
毎日が その繰り返し
The daily routine never changes!
Kaiji must work 15 years in this hidden underground society,
カイジは地上と完全に隔離された
この地下社会で
cut off from all contact with the surface!
15年 働き続けなければならない
クソッ 地上で逃げ回ってる方が
よっぽどマシだ
Dammit... Even just being chased around on the outside would beat this...
But...
だが 脱走しようにも
監視カメラが常に見張っている
Even if I try to escape, the security cameras will catch me.
Even if I fool the cameras and break down that thick door,
仮にあのカメラをごまかして
分厚いドアの向こうに
出たとしても
その先は
複雑に入り組んだ巨大迷路
nothing lies beyond but a labyrinth.
This is an inescapable underground fortress.
脱出不可能な地下要塞
あるいは 看守辺りを
人質にとって脱出しようにも
And even if I take a supervisor hostages,
各班長はもちろん
工事長に至るまで
All the foremen, even the director, are down here because they didn't pay their debt.
皆 借金をカタに連れてこられた
言うなら囚人
They're all prisoners. Useless to ransom.
人質の意味を成さない
全員で反乱する手もあるが
それはどうもありそうにない
It doesn't seem like rioting would do the trick, either.
Not only are the guards strict,
これほどひどい環境にありながら
there's enough of a hierarchy established to hold things down.
一種のヒエラルキーの下
妙に秩序立っている
So my only hope is...
となれば 唯一の希望は
勤労奨励オプション
The hard work bonus.
A one-day vacation!
１日外出券
囚人たちの労働意欲高揚のために
設けた超特例措置
In order to encourage the prisoners to work harder,
special incentives are offered!
One of those is this one-day vacation!
それがこの１日外出券
All I need for that is money.
金さえ出せば あれが手に入る
とにかく１日でも外へ出れば
何とかなる
If I can just get out of here for one day, I'll figure something out.
外にさえ行けば
競馬や競輪 裏カジノ
If I'm out, I can make it to a track, or an illegal casino...
何でもいい　何でもいい！
Anything! Anything would work!
何でも１発 当てさえすれば
Just one win, and I'll pay that ten million back all at once!
1000万ぽっちの借金 屁でもねえ
叩き返せる
But...
しかし…
50万ペリカ
１日外出券を得るには
It costs 500,000 perica!
My ticket out of here for a day is 500,000 perica.
50万ペリカ
クソッ…
Shit!
注目ー！
ん？
Attention!
Great work out there today.
今日も作業 ご苦労さまでした
労働手帳に今日の分のハンコを
押しておきました
I've signed your timecards for today.
お返しします　それと
I'll pass them around.
Oh, and it's finally payday!
今日はお待ちかね 給料日でーす！
Come up and take your pay when I call your name.
名前を呼ばれたら
順番に取りに来てください
His first payday!
初給料
91,000 perica!
９万1000ペリカ
perica are a currency used only in this underworld.
ペリカとはこの地下社会だけで
通用する貨幣単位のこと
Their value is 1/10 that of the yen; that is, 91,000 perica is worth 9,100 yen!
その価値 日本円の10分の１
つまり９万1000ペリカは
9100円ということになる
１ヵ月 筆舌に
尽くしがたい重労働に耐え
In return for a month of backbreaking labor,
わずか9100円
Kaiji receives only 9,100 yen!
Kaiji's debt is 9.5 million yen!
カイジの借金は950万
利息だけで月14万ちょっと
The interest alone is nearly 140,000 yen a month!
無職のカイジには
利息からして支払い不能
Kaiji, with no job, cannot pay even the interest!
But working underground, that usurious interest is forgiven!
しかしこの地下で働くならば
その重い金利はチャラ
Bit by bit, he can begin to pay down that 9.5 million yen!
わずかずつだが 借金の元金
950万を減らしていける
But Kaiji's daily wage is only 3,500 yen!
だが１日働いて支払われる日当は
日本円で3500円
このうち2000円が
借金の返済に充てられ
Of that, 2,000 yen is applied to his debt!
さらに1150円が 食費や
施設利用費などの名目で消える
Another 1,150 yen are taken to pay for room and board!
He receives only a scant tenth of the original 3,500 yen!
手にするのは3500円の10分の１
For a day's labor, only 350 yen!
１日働いて たったの350円
Damn it! This is just insulting!
クソッ ふざけやがって
Meaning everything rests on this!
とはいえ
これに全てが懸かっている
Kaiji's entire future!
カイジの未来 行く末が！
俺にもビール
はい 5000ペリカ
Give me a beer, too!
Sure, that'll be 5,000 perica!
ああ 俺にも！
俺 ロング缶
Me too!
I'll have a tallboy!
はい 6000ペリカ
6,000 perica!
ポテトチップも
はいはい　合計9000ペリカ
And some chips too!
Okay, that'll be 9,000 perica!
I'll have some nuts.
俺は柿ピーね
はいはい
Coming right up.
Those morons!
バカが！欲に流れて
夢も追えないのか
They're throwing away their dreams! Those greedy idiots!
自堕落な連中め！
5,000 perica for a beer? That's 500 yen!
ビール１本5000ペリカ
500円だぞ？
外の倍以上の値段だ
That's more than twice what it costs outside!
あんな調子で使ったら
あっという間にこんな金 消し飛ぶ
They'll blow all their money in no time!
There's no saving people like that.
なのに こいつらときたら
救えねえ　クズが
But I'm different. I'll save.
俺は違う　俺は貯める
At 91,000 perica a month, if I save up for 6 months...
このひと月９万のペリカを
６ヵ月貯めれば
54万ペリカ　あの外出券に届く
That's 540,000 perica! I'll be able to afford my ticket out of here!
That's all I need!
届くんだ！となりゃ 誰が使うか
Who the hell would blow their money with that dangling in front of their faces?
Not me!
使うか！クソッ
Dammit!
だが 頑なになればなるほど
その反動は大きい
But as determined as Kaiji is, he faces stiff opposition!
それにしても 何なんだ
この胸のざわめきは？
It makes perfect sense! So why am I so nervous?
あ… そうよ 買える
俺は買える
I know! I can buy something!
I'll buy something!
I've had nothing all month!
入ってひと月は
どうにもならなかったが
今の俺なら買える
I can afford to buy things now!
Smokes! Chips!
タバコ ポテチ
缶コーヒー 焼き鳥
Coffee! Yakitori!
Even beer!
ビールも
クソッ
Shit!
フフフ… 分かるよ カイジ君
I know how you feel, Kaiji.
は… 班長
外出券だろ？
Foreman!
I used to think I'd go for the ticket out of here too.
考えることは一緒だ
え？
わしも最初 そうだった
You don't wanna spend a single yen here, do you?
となりゃー こんな所で
使っちゃいられねえよなあ
But you can't deprive yourself.
けど 無理はいけねえ
無理は続かない
自分を適度に許すことが
You'll never last if you try to fast.
長続きのコツさ
はあ？
わしのおごりだ
Here, my treat. Let's celebrate your first payday.
カイジ君の初給料のお祝いさ
No need to pay me back.
金は取らねえよ
あ… 班長
Foreman...
ああっ！
キンキンに冷えてやがる！
It's so cold!
ああ… ありがてえ！
Thanks a ton!
I'm so happy I'm crying!
涙が出る
犯罪的だ！うますぎる！
This should be a crime!
It's fucking tasty!
労働の火照りと部屋の熱気で
息苦しい体に
My first beer after suffering a month through the heat and the sweat!
１ヵ月ぶりのビール！
染み込んできやがる
I feel it flowing through my veins!
体に…
I think I'm going to melt!
溶けそうだ
マジ ビール１本のためなら
強盗だって…
I don't care if I have to beg, borrow, or steal...
ああ… あんなもので
ビール飲めたら…
Just one more beer...
ああ… クソーッ
Dammit!
クソッ クソッ
Dammit! Dammit!!!
しかし 買おうと思えば
買えなくもない
Now that I think of it, there's nothing wrong with buying one.
If I earn 90,000 perica a month, that's 540,000 perica in half a year.
１ヵ月の給料が９万ペリカ
６ヵ月貯めれば54万
１日外出券の50万ペリカに届く
The ticket out of here is only 500,000 perica.
てことは ４万余分
So I'm 40,000 over.
I have spare money! And if I have money...
余るってことだ　その気になれば
No! You idiot!
バカ　ダメだ
６ヵ月でたったの４万だぞ
It's only 40,000 and it has to last me half a year!
使うのは よっぽど特別な時
I need to save it for special occasions!
特別な日
Special days!
耐えろ　耐えるんだ
I'll endure! I must endure!
Kaiji endures! Endures desperately!
カイジ 耐える　必死に 耐える
だが…
But!
We've already got him over the edge.
一段落ついたな
ああ
Hi, how can I help you?
はい はい はい
何？何なの？カイジ君
What can I get for you, Kaiji?
Just...
…だけ
は？
Just one...
１本…
１本？
One what?
１本ってそれ ビールかい？
One beer?
ビール350を１本ってことかい？
A twelve-ounce can of beer?
One beer for Kaiji!
はい カイジ君
ビール お買い上げ！
Just one is okay. I've endured a month.
１本はいい
考えてみれば１ヵ月はガマンした
This is a special day.
今日は特別な日
Here you go, nice and chilly!
はい どうぞ　冷えてるよ
で つまみは？
How about a snack to go with it?
は？
せっかく飲むんだよ
You haven't had a drink in ages. It's a waste to just have one beer alone.
ビールだけって 味気ないって
つまもうよ　何でもいいからさ
C'mon, get a snack. We've got anything you'd want.
Then... How about those nuts?
じゃあ そこの柿ピ…
フフフ… ヘタだな カイジ君
You're not any good at this, are you, Kaiji?
え？
ヘタッピさ
No good at all.
欲望の解放のさせ方がヘタ
You need to learn how to let yourself loose.
You know what you really want?
カイジ君が本当に欲しいのは…
This.
これ　これをチンして
ホッカホカにしてさ
A nice hot snack to go with your cold beer.
冷えたビールでやりたい
だろ？
あ…
Right?
フフッ　だけどそれは
あまりに値が張るから
But they're out of your price range, so you're settling for these sorry nuts.
こっちのショボい柿ピーで
ごまかそうっていうんだ
Don't do that to yourself, Kaiji.
カイジ君 ダメなんだよ それじゃ
せっかく冷えたビールで
スカッとしようって時に
Having those with a nice cold beer will just stress you out.
そんなんじゃ
かえってストレスが溜まる
You'll be too worried about the chicken you could've had to relax!
食えなかった焼き鳥が
ちらついてさ
全然スッキリしない
心の毒は残ったままだ
You just won't be able to let it go!
ぜいたくってやつはさ
小出しじゃダメなんだ
If you're going to indulge yourself, you need to go all the way.
やる時ゃ きっちりやった方がいい
When you go for it, really go for it.
それでこそ次の節制の
励みになるってもんさ
It's the only way to encourage yourself.
Now c'mon, give yourself a reward.
自分へのご褒美さ
言われてみれば確かにそうかも
You make it sound so reasonable.
All right...
じゃあ…
はい 焼き鳥 お買い上げ！
One order of yakitori, coming right up!
１分 お待ちください
Just hold on a minute!
実はポテチも…
はい ポテチもお買い上げ！
Honestly, I'd like some chips too...
Potato chips too!
If you're having that much you're gonna need another beer.
となると ビール１本じゃ
全然 足りないよね？
うまあっ！
This is great!
うー 最高！
It's awesome!
いつも貧しい食事ばっかだから
Compared to those terrible rations,
this convenience store yakitori and nikujaga just sticks to the ribs!
こんなコンビニの焼き鳥や
肉じゃがが染みる… 染みる！
くーっ！ってビールが…
This beer!
フッフッフ…
バカ丸出しですね
The idiot's going all-out.
バカだからね あんなもんよ
今の若いもんなんて
That's because he's an idiot. Kids these days are like that.
Once he's full and happy, he'll say this to himself.
食べ終わったら 奴はとりあえず
満足してこう考えるだろう
"I'll work harder tomorrow. I'll start saving tomorrow."
｢明日から頑張ろう｣
｢明日から節約だ｣と
But that's not a good way to think.
まあ その考え方がダメ
明日から頑張るんじゃない
今日　今日だけ頑張るんだ
You don't work harder tomorrow. You work harder today.
Those who work hard today...
今日を頑張った者
今日を頑張り始めた者にのみ
明日が来るんだよ
Those who work hard today are the only ones who have a tomorrow.
また１人 確保ってことですね
So he's gonna be here for a while, then?
ああ　ってことになるな
Yeah, I guess.
This food is the only pleasure we're allowed.
ここにはこの｢食｣以外
他に快楽がない
So its temptation is extremely powerful.
ゆえに その誘惑は強烈
Once you fall for it once, you're doomed.
一度 知ったらもう抗えない
結局のところ
｢ちょっと１杯｣ってのが
You're a fool if you think you'll just have one on special occasions.
大甘なのよ
And that one can is your first step on your tumble into this abyss.
その１杯がこの底辺のさらに底辺
底の底へ転がり落ちる最初の一歩
入り口
A one-way entrance.
そしてカイジ 豪遊！
Kaiji goes wild!
４万1000ペリカの散財！
He blows 41,000 perica!
Yes, in the end...
そう　結局のところ
In this world, there are only two kinds of people:
世の中は利用する側とされる側
その２種類しかいないのだ
Those who use and those who are used!
The only question is the obvious—when will he realize!?
問題は その当たり前に
いつ気づくかだ
(笛の音)
作業終了
Shift over!
はい ビールお待ち
はい 毎度どうも
One beer, coming right up!
Thanks!
こちら5000ペリカ
That'll be 5,000 perica!
フッ 座禅組んで
欲望の火が消えりゃあ
Trying Zen meditation to stave off his desires? I guess that works for a lot of people.
誰も苦労しねえんだよ
But I give him about 30 minutes.
まっ 持って30分ってとこか
Kaiji contemplates!
カイジ 反省！
ダメだ！この状況から
６ヵ月で50万貯めるとなると
No!
If I want to get out of here in six months, I can't spend any more money!
使える金は もうない
そりゃ給料の端数の
1000や2000は使えなくもないが…
I guess I could spend the extra 1000s from my pay, but...
ハア…
６ヵ月 何にも使えないなんて
いや というより
I can't stand not buying anything for a whole month...
I've already blown my plan not to spend any more than 40,000 over six months!
もともと６ヵ月で
４万しか使えないという計画に
無理があったんだ
７ヵ月？そうだ ７ヵ月にすれば
Maybe if I take seven months?
That's it! If I take seven months I'll be able to reach 500,000!
無理なく50万に届く
なら 少しはいいか…
So I can indulge myself just a little...
はい カイジ君
ビール お買い上げ！
One beer for Kaiji!
One beer, coming right up!
ビール１本
気がつけば 豪遊！
When Kaiji came to...
He realized he had gone wild again!
２日 続けて豪遊
For the second time in as many days!
またやってしまった
He did it again!
カイジ 猛省！
Kaiji searches his soul!
But even as he does so, he spends more and more over the next two days,
しかし 猛省しつつも
翌日 翌々日とチビチビ使い
And on the fifth day!
そして５日目 残金400ペリカ
Kaiji has only 400 perica left!
He has arrived at the tearful conclusion!
ついに来たトホホな状況
He can buy only twelve peanuts!
買えるのは ばら売りの柿ピー
３粒100ペリカを４回
給料日まで25日
There are 25 days left until payday! Can his desires be sated with half a peanut a day!?
ぜいたくは柿ピー１日
半かけらという計算
ああ… ハア…
Ohtsuki, the foreman, makes his next move!
そして班長の大槻は次の手に出る
Wanna borrow some cash?
借りる？
給料の前借りさ　わしが請け負う
I'll give you an advance on your pay.
しかし そんなことしたら…
But if you do that...
なあに 借りて 今度こそ
無理なく使っていけばいいんだよ
You really should go ahead and borrow.
If you don't, you're just going to be depriving yourself until next payday.
もし借りなきゃ カイジ君は
次の給料日まで
禁欲生活ってことになる
That's not good for you, you know.
その禁欲ってのがよくないんだ
Kaiji, this is a rubber ball.
カイジ君 心はゴムだよ
押さえつければ
必ず跳ね返そうとする
Press it, and it springs back.
Meaning... If you try to hold yourself back, you'll just blow it all the moment you get paid.
つまり いくら頑張っても
給料が入ると その禁欲の反動で
また豪遊してしまうんだ
そういうもんなんだよ
That's how it is.
それより今 ６もらってだな
６？
So how about borrowing sixty?
Sixty?
Well, it's an advance, so it's not like I can give you the whole ninety.
前借りだからね
９万全部ってわけにはいかない
それ相応の手数料を
もらわないとね
There needs to be something in it for me, you know?
What if they move one of us to a different group?
突然の配置換えがあったり
貸した相手に寝込まれたりと
Or if you just quit working or something. I'm taking a risk too.
結構 こっちには
取りっぱぐれのリスクがあるんだ
しかし ６ってのは…
But sixty is...
まあまあ 足りないのは
自分で補えばいいじゃないか
If you don't think it's enough, you can always earn some more for yourself.
噂じゃカイジ君は
相当の腕だって聞いてるよ
I've heard you're pretty good.
How about it? Why not get back to your old habits tonight?
どうだい？今夜辺り
こいつで復活っていうのは？
A devil beckons in the abyss!
地の底の底で悪魔が誘う
サイコロ賭博 チンチロリン！
The dice game chinchirorin!
Just one win,
I don't think of this an an anime, I think of it as a play.
I put all of my energy into each performance!
Proverbs of Kaiji returns!
Don't miss it!